World War I Collection
World War I Collection
1912-1964
1914-1919
0.25 linear ft.
Published material, clippings and ephemera relating to World War I.
3367127
Biographical History
World War I (1914-1918), originally known as the World War, the Great War, or the War to End All Wars until 1939, involved all major powers in the world at the time. It was triggered by the assassination of Arch-Duke Franz Ferdinand, but the imperialistic policies of Germany, England, France, Italy and Russia in the preceding decades played an important role in setting the stage. On one side were the Allies (at first Russia, England and France, later joined by the United States, Canada, Spain, and several other countries) and on the other the Central Powers (primarily the German Empire, the Austro-Hungarian Empire and the Ottoman Empire). Hostilities ceased on 11 November 1918 (Armistice Day) and the war formally ended on June 28, 1919 with the signing of the Treaty of Versailles.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The World War I Collection consists of printed material and personal material.
Personal material consists of a diary (1918-1919) and accompanying memorabilia, including dance tickets and reminiscent notes, and a number of postcards from Harold Drais, with the 56th Engineers, to his family.
Printed material contains cartoons and clippings from German newspapers; a 1964 issue of LIFE magazine with the cover story "The First World War"; an assortment of pro-German pamphlets, some in German and others in English; miscellaneous post-war American and English pamphlets; souvenir postcards with photographs of World War I battlefields, memorials and cemeteries; and a few miscellaneous items. Of particular interest among the pamphlets are two from 1915: The British Black Book, by "an American", and a piece by Houston Stewart Chamberlain entitled, "Who is to blame for the war?"
Arrangement of the Collection
Series are arranged alphabetically. Within that, clippings are arranged chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Military history; Chamberlain, Houston Stewart, 1855-1927 -- Who is to blame for the war?; Cronau, Rudolf -- The British black book.; Drais, Harold J. -- Correspondence.; United States. -- Army. -- Engineer Regiment, 56th.; Château-Thierry, Battle of, Château-Thierry, France, 1918.; World War, 1914-1918.; Compiègne Forest (France); Montfaucon (Meuse, France); Cartoons (humorous images); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Diaries.; Editorial cartoons.; Pamphlets.; Postcards.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Various.
Inventory
- Personal material
  - Correspondence, Harold Drais, 1919; picture postcards sent to family (Box 1)
  - Diary and related memorabilia, 1918-1919; undated; dance ticket, news clipping (Box 1)
- Printed material
  - Cartoons, German, 1914-1919; cartoons published in German newspapers; humorous as well as editorial (Box 1)
  - Clippings
    - English-language newspapers, relating to the Titanic, 1912 (Box 1)
    - German newspapers, relating to the war, 1914-1916 (Box 1)
    - Anti-war editorial by George Bernard Shaw, published in New York American, 1919 (Box 1)
    - German newspapers, relating to the war, also one or two in English, Undated (Box 1)
  - Magazine, LIFE, 1964; cover story on World War I (Oversize 1)
  - Pamphlets
    - Pro-German publications, 1914-1916; in English; primarily text, few or no photos; includes "The British Black Book" outlining why England should be America's enemy and "Who is to blame for the war?" by Houston Stewart Chamberlain (Box 1)
    - Pro-German publications, 1914-1916; in German; many with photographs and illustrations (Oversize 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1931; 1934,; undated; Sermon "The Slaugher of the Innocents" by Father Charles Coughlin; pamphlet on the war and the American farmer; booklet "Arms and the Men" about Krupp and other arms manufacturers' role in the war (Box 1)
  - Postcards, battlefields, memorials, cemeteries (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, War Chest ad, EGGNIT egg substitute ad, large printed photo, possibly an oversize postcard (Box 1)